是, 大臣  第3季第1集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:achogogo 校对&时间轴:tpring
机会均等
就象我说的 凯西 首相想要我加入内阁
So, Kathy, the Prime Minister saw fit to invite one into the Cabinet
我就进来了
and, well, here one is.
责任很重大吧?
Isn't it a terrific responsibility?
依我看 一个人选择毕生为公众服务
I suppose, if one chooses to dedicate one's life to public service,
就要担起这份责任
responsibility is something one accepts.
权力很大啊      我知道 我知道
But all this power! I know, I know!
有时让人受宠若惊 但又让人谦卑自省
Frightening sometimes. But it also makes one very humble.
一旦坐在首相府 内阁会议桌前 顿时发现...
Sits at the Cabinet table, Number 10 Downing Street and realises
伯纳打电话来 谦卑的人
Bernard rang, O humble one.
下议院要你看BBC二台
Central House want you to watch a programme on BBC2.
莫琳沃金 国会议员 后座议员之一
Maureen Watkins, MP. One of the backbench MPs.
我不太喜欢她 整天喊女权 算了我不看 别写进去
A rampaging feminist. I wont bother. Don't write that down.
我喜欢她 您不觉得女性仍然是弱势群体?
I like her. Don't you think that women are still the exploited sex?
我们全班都觉得女性在单位被剥削 在家被剥削
All of us in 5B think that women are exploited at work and at home
整个社会被男性主导 运行 男性为所欲为
it's a world designed and run by men for men's convenience.
就象她说的      现在肯定不会了
Like SHE says. Not any longer, surely?
她在下院没分量      当然 那被男人占据了
She doesn't carry any weight in the House. No, it's full of men.
多谢了安妮 还要问什么吗?      最后一个问题
Thank you. Anything else you'd like to ask? Just one last question.
作为执掌大权的大臣 您有什么个人成就?
As a minister, what have you personally achieved?
成就? 很多啦
Achieved? Oh, well, all sorts of things.
枢密院席位 党内政策委员会...
Membership of the Privy Council, the Party Policy Committee...
不 你做的实事 有惠于人民的
No, things you've done that makes life better for other people.
有惠于?      对
Makes life better? Yes.
其他人? 当然有很多了
For other people? There must be a number of things.
这就是职责所在嘛 一天18个小时 没有双休日
That's what one's job is all about. 18 hours a day, 7 days a week.
可以举个事例吗?
Could you give me examples?
不然写出来很无聊的      事例
Makes it a bit boring otherwise. Examples.
不知道从哪说起 太多政府的协同决策了
Where to start. So much of government is collective decisions.
我们聚到一起 整个国家最出色的头脑 群策群力
All of us together, best minds in the country, hammering it out.
但什么让你回想往事的时候 骄傲的说"我做的"
But what will you look back on afterwards and say "I did that."
就象作家回顾自己的作品一样
You know, like a writer can look at his books.
政府是个精密的机器 人们各执一词
Government is a complex business people have to have their say.
都需要时间 罗马不是一天建成的...是现在吗?
Take time. Rome wasn't built in a day. Is that the time?
我得看电视节目 失陪了
I really must be getting my boxes. Excuse me.
谢谢      非常感谢
Oh, thank you. Thank you so much.
跟你聊天真有意思 写出来给我审阅一下 可以吗?
Such fun this little talk. Let me approve the article, as we agreed?
拜      拜
Bye. Bye.
小大人
Bright kid.
再也不接受校报采访了 她问的问题太难了
Last interview for a school magazine. She asked difficult questions.
只是天真而已 她觉得你凭良心做事
She assumed there was some moral basis to your activities.
当然了      喔 吉姆 别傻了!
Well, there is. Oh, Jim, don't be silly!
你叹什么气?
What are you sighing for?
我没叹气
I'm not sighing.
说来听听      我有什么成就? 她问得对
Out with it. Well, what have I achieved? She's right.
你还真谦卑起来啦      我一条法案都没通过
It really does make you humble! I can't get any bills through.
还有两年就要卸任了      改革公务员系统
The time's taken up for the next two years. Reform the Civil Service.
不可能的 是个怪圈      为什么
Impossible. Catch 22. Why?
就算我提出50条重大改革 谁来实施它们?
I suggested 50 terrific reforms, who would have to implement them?
公务员系统
(BOTH) The Civil Service.
这样 我跟你说
All right, I tell you what.
不要50个改革 一个就够了
Not 50 reforms, just one.
哼 什么?
Huh! What?
完成一项重大改革 你就很了不起了
If you achieve one import reform, that'd be something.
我会载入史册 你有什么建议?
Get me in the record books! What do you suggest?
多提拔女性进入高层
Make them put more women into top jobs.
女性占人口的一半 也应该占常任秘书的一半
Half the population Should be half the Permanent Secretaries.
高层有多少女性?      不是很多
How many women are there at the top? Not many.
机会均等
Equal opportunities.
值得一试 不管怎样 这是原则问题
I'll have a go. After all, there's a principle at stake.
你要全凭原则做一些实事?
You're going to do something out of pure principle?
对      喔 吉姆
Yes. Oh, Jim.
原则问题最刺激选票
Principles are excellent vote winners.
我们什么都不用做?      不用 第一第二段有误
We don't have to do anything? No. Paragraphs 1 and 2 are wrong.
其他都规定好了 不能改
And all the other points are covered.
我不需要做决定 还不用道歉
I don't have to make a decision. I don't even have to apologise.
能帮我拟一份回复吗?      已经完成了
Can you do a reply for me? Done it.
太好了 你这样的副秘书怎么这么少呢?
Fantastic. Why don't they make more Under-Secretaries like you?
还有别的事吗 大臣?      没了
Anything else, Minister? No.
告诉我 莎拉 高级公务员里有多少位女性?
How many women are there at the top of the Civil Service?
常任秘书里没有 150位常务副秘书里有4位
No Permanent Secretaries. Four out of 150 Deputy Secretaries.
你这一级 副秘书里呢?      27位女性
What about your grade? Under-Secretary? There are 27 of us.
好像还可以 一共多少人?      578人
Doesn't sound too bad. Out of how many? 578.
太不像话了 你没想法吗?     还行吧 觉得很滑稽
But that's appalling! Aren't you appalled? I find it comic.
不过公务员工作本来就滑稽 男人控制的嘛
But then I find most of the Civil Service comic. It's run by men
你能做什么 我能做什么?
What can you? What can I do?
您说真的 大臣?      对
Are you serious, Minister? Yes.
很简单 把各行各业的精英女性招进来
Bring top women from the professions, Straight into the top grades.
工资高 假期长 养老金 会有出色人选的
The pay is good for women. You'd get high-quality applicants.
他们能胜任?      当然能
And they could do the job? Of course.
恕我直言 一个报业议员可以晋升大臣
With respect, if you can make a journalist MP into a minister,
高级律师怎么就不能当副秘书?
why not make a partner from a legal firm into an Under-Secretary?
再说了 这的工作两个初中文凭就可以胜任
Most of the work here only needs about two O-levels, anyway.
有道理 莎拉 十分感谢      谢谢 大臣
Good point. Sarah, thank you very much. Thank you, Minister.
你叫我 大臣?      伯纳 莎拉告诉我...
You rang, Minister? Bernard, Sarah told...
什么 大臣?      没人的时候就叫我吉姆
Yes, Minister? I wish you'd call me Jim when we're alone.
我会记住的 大臣
Oh, I'll try to remember that, Minister.
莎拉告诉我这个申诉没道理
Sarah tells me this complaint is nonsense.
很好 我们可以CGSM了它      CGSM?
Oh, fine. So we can CGSM it. CGSM?
公务员术语 意思是"老年鞋厂委托书"
Civil service code. Consignment of Geriatric Shoe Manufacturers.
一大堆无用功 大臣
Load of old cobblers, Minister.
我不是公务员 我有我的术语 我写"转圜否决"
I shall use my own code. I shall write "round objects".
大臣 您要讨论员工问题?
Ah, Minister, you wanted a word about staffing?
没错 汉弗莱      早安 伯纳
Yes, Humphrey. Morning, Bernard.
我制订了一项新政
I've made a policy decision.
我要在公务员中女性数量上做文章
I'm going to change the number of women in the Civil Service.
反正数量也不多
Surely there aren't all that many.
问题就在这里      大臣觉得要多招一些
That's my point. The Minister thinks we need more.
多招很多      很多?
Many more. More?
打字员 清洁工 茶点工都满员了 你觉得呢 伯纳?
We're up to establishment on typists and tea ladies. Any ideas?
我们临时秘书人手不够      我在说常任秘书
Short on temporary secretaries. I'm talking Permanent Secretaries.
常任...      需要一批女官(又意甜橙)
Permanent... We need female mandarins.
那是无籽芦柑 大臣
Sort of satsumas, Minister.
坐下好吗 伯纳
Sit down, will you, Bernard.
常任秘书有多少人?      41个
How many Permanent Secretaries are there? 41, I believe.
其中有多少女性呢?      呃 基本上说...
And how many of those are women? Well, broadly speaking...
手上没有数据 我不好说
Not having the figures to hand, I'm not sure.
大约呢      大约...没有
Approximately. Approximately... none.
没有 我们有大约150位副秘书 多少女性?
There are about 150 Deputy Secretaries. How many are women?
这很难说      为什么?
Well, it's difficult to say. Why?
有很多男人婆婆妈妈的
There's a lot of old women among the men.
4位      这么多啊?
Four. Are there really?
我要宣布女性副秘书和常任秘书增加到25%
A quota of 25% women Deputy and Permanent Secretaries
四年内完成
to be achieved in four years.
等一等 大臣 我肯定赞成你的提议
Wait. I'm obviously in total sympathy with your objectives.
肯定的      当然我们需要更多女性
Obviously. Of course we must have more women.
肯定的 我们都很关心性别不平等问题
Of course! We are deeply concerned by this apparent imbalance,
但这些事要花时间的
but these things take time.
我希望马上着手      我举双手同意
I want to make a start straight away. I agree.
就从设立部门协调委员会入手...
I propose we setting up an inter-departmental committee...
不不不 你知道我不是这个意思
No, no, no. That's not what I meant and you know it.
不许拖延 要手持大锤 果断斩乱麻
This needs a sledgehammer. We must cut through the red tape.
大锤不能斩乱麻...      你知道我的意思
You can't cut tape with a sledgehammer... You know what I mean.
大臣 你误会我了 我没有要拖延
You do me an injustice. I was not about to suggest delays.
喔 抱歉      没关系
Oh, sorry. That's all right.
我的意见是 如果我们要25%的配额
I suggest that, if we are to have 25% quota,
招募规模要比这大得多 最终才能招到25%
Larger intake at the stage so there'll be 25% in the top jobs.
多久?      25年
When? (BOTH) In 25 years.
不 汉弗莱 你还没明白我的决心 我要马上
No, Humphrey, you haven't quite got my drift. I mean NOW.
您是说 马上?      真有悟性 汉弗莱
Oh... you mean, NOW? Got it in one, Humphrey.
大臣 马上做事需要时间
It takes time to do things NOW.
公务员工作三原则 越拖延越高效
3 articles of Civil Service : takes longer to do things quickly;
越费钱越便宜 越秘密越民主
more expensive to do them cheaply, more democratic in secret.
我建议四年完成 时间充足
I have suggested four years. Masses of time.
我的天 不行
Oh, dear me, no!
不是政治时间 我指现实时间
I don't mean political time, I mean real time.
公务员的增长...像大树一样 不是像韭菜
Civil servants are grown like oak trees, not mustard and cress.
随季节开花生长 他们的成熟就像...
They bloom and ripen with the seasons, they mature like...
像你自己      我刚想说像醇酒
Like yourself. Well, I was about to say like an old port.
要酿上一酿?
Like Grimsby, perhaps.
对 我是认真的 大臣      我早料到了
Yes, I was being serious, Minister. I foresaw this problem.
我看这好办 外聘女性精英
By bringing in top women from outside the service
来填补高层职缺
to fill vacancies in the top jobs.
我...
I...
我不明白      看我的嘴形 汉弗莱
I don't think I quite understood. Watch my mouth, Humphrey.
我们从编制外招募女性
We will bring in women from outside.
但这个体制强大之处就在于它的纯洁及独立
But the strength is that it is unsullied by outside influences.
人人都能跳槽 公务员行业有什么特殊?
People move jobs. Why should the Civil Service be different?
它确实特殊 它要求微妙
It IS different. It demands subtlety.
判断力      无私的奉献
Discretion. Devotion to duty.
可靠      可靠 说得好 伯纳
Soundness. Soundness! Well said, Bernard!
公务员需要具有超人的毅力和宽广的胸襟
Endless patience and boundless understanding.
他们可以迎难而上
They need to be able to change horses mid-stream,
紧密跟随政客 与时俱进
as politicians change what they call their minds.
这些特性你都有了?      我只是恰好...
You have these talents? Well, it is just that one's been properly
被人给酿了 就像酒      受过训练
Matured. Like Grimsby. Trained.
你扪心自问 要是体制没问题
Ask yourself if there isn't something wrong with the system.
为什么没有女性官员?      她们离职生孩子去了
Why are there so few women? They keep leaving to have babies.
50多岁生孩子?不会吧      我不知道 我听您的
At nearly 50? Surely not. I don't know. I'm on your side.
高层确实需要更多女性      好 我不会等25年
We do need more women at the top. I'm not waiting 25 years.
副秘书有个空缺吧?      对
There's a vacancy for Deputy Secretary here. Ye-es.
我要任命一位女性 莎拉哈里森      莎拉哈里森?
I shall appoint a woman. Sarah Harrison. Sarah Harrison?!
我看她很有能力 你看呢?     是有能力
I think she's very able? Very.
作为女性 作为一个人
For a woman, for a person.
想问题很有创意
And she is an original thinker.
恐怕是的 幸好她不带到工作中来
Yes, that's true, but she doesn't let it interfere with her work.
你对她有什么意见?      没有 她很出色
What have you got against her? Nothing. She's excellent.
我很看好她
I'm a supporter of hers.
去年就是我最先提出晋升她当副秘书
I advocated her promotion to Under-Secretary at a very early age.
你同意她十分出色吗?      同意
Would you agree that she is outstanding? Yes.
那平衡利弊 这是可行的?     平衡利弊 行也不行
So, on balance, it is a good idea? On balance... yes and no.
这不是明确答复      这是平衡答复
That's not a very clear answer. It's a balanced answer.
问题是她还年轻 还没轮到她
The point is she's too young and it's not her turn.
就知道你会说 这就是公务员的问题 论资排辈
This is exactly what's wrong with the Civil Service Buggins' turn!
好的人才就要赶快提拔     没错 只要轮到他们
The best people should be promoted As soon as it's their turn!
一派胡言 拿破仑30岁就统治欧洲了
Oh, nonsense! Napoleon ruled Europe when he was in his 30s!
亚历山大20岁征服世界     他们做不了副秘书
Alexander conquered the world at 20s They made poor Secretaries.
他们没有论资排辈      看看他们的下场
They didn't wait their turn! And look what happened to them.
看看我们的问题
And look what's happened to us!
治国的不是被年轻有为 有活力的人
Instead of being run by a lot of young, able, energetic men,
而是一群疲惫 刻薄的老头 只想安享晚年
this country's being run by 55-year-olds who just want a quiet life!
您在暗示谁吗?
Had you anyone specific in mind?
是又不是 汉弗莱
Yes and no, Humphrey.
大臣 莎拉哈里森是位出色的公务员 前途光明
Sarah Harrison is an excellent civil servant, a hope for the future,
但她是资历最浅的副秘书 最好不要提拔
but she is our most junior and I will not recommend her promotion.
我觉得你性别歧视      大臣 这话怎讲?
I think you're a sexist. Minister, how could you say such a thing?
我支持女人 女人很美好
I'm very pro-women. Wonderful people, women.
莎拉是位可爱的女士 我对她景仰之至
Sarah is a dear lady. I'm one of her greatest admirers.
但如果要推进女权 必须小心谨慎
the cause of women must be done with care, tact and discretion.
女性高官就她一个人选 不能急功近利
She is our only woman for a top job. We mustn't push her too fast.
高层职务对女性太难了     听听你这什么话
Women find top jobs very difficult. Can you hear yourself?
如果她们能胜任 就不会这么少 顺理成章的
If they could be good Permanent Secretaries there would be more.
不 汉弗莱...      我不反女权 我爱女人
No... I'm not anti-feminist! I love women!
我有很要好的女性朋友
Some of my best friends are women!
比如我妻子就是女的
Er... my wife, indeed.
但莎拉经验不足 而且孩子还在上学
But Sarah is inexperienced and her children are still of school age.
他们可能会得腮腺炎      你还得神经炎呢
They might get mumps! You might get shingles!
您再说我马上就要得了 万一她为孩子旷工呢?
Indeed if you continue. What if children caused her to miss work?
那她还能当上副秘书? 她是人中精英
Would she have reached Under-Secretary? She is the best person!
大臣 如果您提拔她只因为她是精英
If you promote women just because they're the best person,
您会造成公务员里怨言四起
you will create a lot of resentment throughout the Civil Service!
至少女性不会有怨言     可以忽略 不是吗?
Not from the women in it. Well, that hardly matters, does it?
可以忽略 汉弗莱?
Hardly matters?
她们人太少了
There are so few of them.
我试图说服他女性和我们不一样 他没法明白
I've told him women are different, but he can't grasp it.
她们太拖团队的后腿
They put such strains on a team.
她们对事态度不同 她们太感性 不如我们理性
They react differently. They're so emotional. Not rational like us.
还不能明说 不然她们要么嚼舌头要么掉眼泪
Hopeless when tell them off. Either into a bate or blubbing.
不掉眼泪的就撒泼
If not the sort who blub, they become frightfully hard and butch.
一点都不迷人
Not the least bit attractive.
她们偏见很多      总是武断的以偏概全
They're full of prejudices. Make silly generalisations.
想事都一个路数      嗯...
They think in stereotypes. (BOTH) Mmm.
阿诺德 你觉得我应该怎么办?
Arnold, what do you think I should do?
我只能建议不停给他灌输 直到他烦了
Lecture him at such length on the matter that he becomes bored
觉得这个想法无趣了
and loses interest in the idea.
对 也许有用 不过他可不容易烦
Yes, might work. Mind you, he doesn't get bored easily.
他甚至都不烦他自己      总会烦的
He even finds himself interesting. They all do.
只要是听他们说话的人      听的人可不多
All the ones who listen to what we're saying. Not many of those.
标准2号方案 是说工会不接受
The standard second ploy is to tell him the unions won't wear it.
工会会接受的      那不重要 汉弗莱
They'd like it. That's beside the point.
喔 抱歉      他妻子会怎么想呢?
Oh, yes, sorry. What does his wife think about all this?
听说他妻子挺支持的 也许她是幕后推手
I gather she's in favour of itn. In fact, she may be behind it.
我明白了 她知不知道哈里森很迷人呢?
I see. Does she know that Sarah Harrison is rather attractive?
不 她们好像没见过...
No, I don't think they've ever met...
好主意
Good idea.
必须发动内阁来反对这个鬼定额
We must mobilise the Cabinet against this quota nonsense.
内阁会欢迎的      我们让他们改主意
They'll be in favour of it. We can get them to change their minds.
他们很容易改主意      就象女人一样
They change their minds fairly easily. Just like a lot of women!
幸好内阁不掉眼泪
Thank God they don't blub!
大臣 我觉得您说的是对的
Minister, I have come to the conclusion that you were right.
你说真的 汉弗莱?      没错 大臣
Are you being serious? Yes, indeed.
您的计划已提上日程 我现在积极反对性别歧视
I am now positively against discrimination against women
同时积极支持性别优待 当然是有差别的优待
In favour of positive discrimination discriminating discrimination
对...我好像明白了
Yes... I think I've got that.
据说最高层的看法是 这个问题要解决
The view is, at the very highest level, that this should happen.
很好      不过...
Good. However...
定额有些问题 介意我坐下吗? 工会无法接受
Problem about the quota. The unions won't wear it.
真的? 叫他们来 我来谈      不行 大臣
Really? Let's have 'em in. We'll talk about it. Er... no, Minister.
那就捅了马蜂窝了      为什么?
That would... just stir up a hornets' nest. Why?
恕我直言 我们得现实点
Well, if I might suggest... that we be realistic about this.
现实点 你意思是全盘放弃      天啊 不是
By realistic, you mean drop the whole scheme. Oh, dear me, no!
也许应当暂缓 重新整顿
But, perhaps, a pause to re-group.
慢慢评估现状 商讨其它战略
Reassess the situation and discuss alternative strategies.
慢慢深思熟虑
A space of time for reflection and deliberation.
你就是说全盘放弃
You mean drop the whole scheme.
不 汉弗莱 我决心已定 马上着手
No, I've set my hand to the plough, I've made the decision.
4年内实现25%女性公务员
We shall have a 25% quota of women within the next four years
就从任命莎拉哈里森为副秘书开始
and, to make a start, I shall appoint Sarah Harrison.
我向您保证 这是犯错误     原则 汉弗莱 原则
That is the wrong decision. Principle, Humphrey, principle.
内阁同僚都说支持我 女权赢得很多选票
I'm sure Cabinet will support me. A lot of votes in women's rights.
选票 大臣? 您不是说为原则吗
Votes? I thought you said it was a matter of principle.
对我是原则 汉弗莱 对他们是选票
For ME. I was talking about them.
喂
Yes?
哈克太太来了 大臣      请她进来好吗
Mrs Hacker's here. Send her in.
请她进来 您能不能先把信件签了 大臣?
Could you sign the letters before you go, Minister?
亲爱的 让汉弗莱给你点喝的     雪利酒?
Hello. Get Humphrey to give you a drink. Sherry?
还记得您批"转圜否决"那个文件吗?
Remember that letter you wrote "round objects" on?
汉弗莱爵士回复并批注了
Sir Humphrey has commented on it.
说什么?     "转圜是谁 他否决什么"?
What's he say? "Who is Round and to what does he object?"
拿着 你气色不错
Here you are. Your very good health.
改革公务员系统要慢工出细活的
Yes, it's a slow business changing the Civil Service.
吉姆说要提拔的那个女性呢?
What about promoting this woman Jim was talking about?
对 您丈夫确实慧眼识珠 莎拉很有才华
Your husband certainly has an eye for talent, Sarah's very talented.
美丽又迷人 干杯      真的?
Quite delightful, real charmer. Cheers. Really?
我真佩服新一代的女性公务员
I very much admire this new generation of women civil servants
和从前那些老顽固相比
compared to the old battle-axes I remember!
当然 她们不见得有莎拉好看 不过都很有女人味
Not all as beautiful as Sarah but they keep their femininity.
吉姆从没说过她长什么样     大概他没注意
Jim never discussed what she looks like. Perhaps he hasn't noticed.
真难以相信 他们两个总泡在一起
I find that hard to believe. He does spend a lot of time with her.
如果她晋升还会更...坐下好吗?
And even more... if she's promoted. Shall we sit down?
先生们 我们大臣决定创造25%的女性定额
Gentlemen, my minister is set on creating a quota of 25% women,
最终达到50%
leading to an eventual 50%.
公平 我明白了      对 嗯
Parity, I see. Yes. Mm.
在我看来男女确实应该平等对待
It seems right to me that women be treated fairly and equally.
大家要达成共识 原则上
I speak for all of us when I say that, in principle,
应该规定定额 达到这个目标     对对
there should be such targets set and goals achieved.
比尔?      我十分赞同这个想法
Bill? Well, I'm fully in favour of this idea.
我们必须对女性特别优待
We must have positive discrimination in favour of women.
但在外交部行不通
It wouldn't work with the Foreign Office.
不能派女性大使到伊朗那样的穆斯林国家
We couldn't post women ambassadors to Iran or Muslim nations.
没错 没错      第三世界比我们落后
No, quite, quite. The Third World is not so advanced as us.
外交官每三年都要换届
We have to send diplomats to new postings every three years,
我们部行不通 但我从原则上支持
this idea is obviously not for us, but I do approve the principle.
尼尔?      我十分赞同
Neil? I'm in favour of it.
增加些女性有好处
I think we need the feminine touch.
女性处理某些事有独到之处 毫无疑问
Women are better at handling some problems than men.
但内务部是个例外
We would have to make an exception in the Home Office.
女人不适合看监狱 做警察
Women are not the right people to run prisons or the police.
很有可能她们自己也不想做
Quite probably, they wouldn't want to do it, anyway.
但你从原则上赞成?      当然 毫无疑问的
But you do agree with the principle? Oh, yes, without question.
皮特?      唉 国防部也一样
Peter? Yes, the same applies to Defence... alas.
管的全是陆海军大将
All those admirals and generals.
女人做不了安全部的头目
It wouldn't be possible to appoint a woman as Head of Security.
男的得变成女的
M would have to become F.
国防部是男人的天下 工业和就业部也一样
Yes, Defence is clearly a man's world, like Industry and Employment.
那些工会领袖
All those trade union leaders!
卫生和社会事务部呢 约翰?
But what about the DHSS? John?
很高兴地说 卫生部高层女性够多了
Woman are well represented near the top of the DHSS.
毕竟 白厅里4个女副秘书我们占2个
After all, we have two of the four Deputy Secretaries in Whitehall.
她们不够格做常务秘书 都是副总医务官
Not eligible for Permanent Secretary. Deputy Chief Medical Officers.
我不觉得他们适合 那不公平
I'm not sure they're really suitable. No, that's unfair.
当然了 80%书记员 99%打字员都是女性
Women are 80% of our clerical staff and 99% of the typing grades.
我们成绩不错 原则上说 我支持她们进入高层
We're not doing too badly. In principle, I'm in favour of it.
很好 很好
Good, good.
会议结论是 从原则出发 我们都赞成
The feeling of the meeting is, in principle we're all in favour
女士们的平等权益
of equal rights for the ladies,
但特定部门里有特殊境况
but there are special problems in individual departments.
是 是      那定额问题怎么办?
(ALL) Hear hear! What about this question of the quota?
老实说 我不太同意      对 不赞成
Frankly, I'm against it. (ALL) Oh, yes, not on!
我们得有权提拔最有能力的人才
We must have the right to promote the best man for the job,
无论性别
regardless of sex.
我作为一个热忱的女权主义者
Speaking as an ardent feminist myself,
觉得问题在于招收哪种女性
I think the problem lies in recruiting the right sort of women.
已婚有家室的就不行
Married women with families drop out
她们不能全身心投入到工作中去
because they cannot give their work their full attention.
未婚无子女的
Unmarried women with no children
不够成熟 涉世未深
are not fully-rounded people with a thorough understanding of life.
实践中不可能找到成熟的
It's rarely possible to find a fully-rounded married woman,
已婚育有三个孩子 全心全意工作的女性
with a home and 3 children, devote her whole life to a department.
就是22条军规第一项 精神不健全可以免出勤
It's Catch 22, really. Well, Catch 22, sub-paragraph A!
我觉得要让内阁大臣们否决这个提案
We must ensure that our ministers oppose this quota idea
就要各自讲清各部特殊情况
by drawing their attention to each department's special problems.
但各级部门都要从原则上赞同
But we will recommend the principle of equal at every level.
我再说一句好吗?
May I suggest one more thing?
我们大臣还把提拔女性看作是
My minister sees the promotion as creating greater diversity
在公务员高层实现多元化
at the top of the service.
要使他们明白 说真的 我们已经很多元化了
Stress to our ministers that there's no more diverse lot than us.
绝对的      跨越行业的典范
(ALL) Absolutely! A real cross-section of the nation.
大臣 内阁会议怎样?
Ah, Minister, how was Cabinet?
很怪 真的      为什么?
Bit odd, actually. Why?
我们讨论了女性高层定额的事
We were talking about the top jobs quota for women.
同意了吗?      怪就怪在这
Was it agreed? That's what's so odd.
原则上都支持 但在他们自己部里行不通
Agreed in principle, but said it wouldn't work in their departments.
他们一点都不支持我      太怪了
They didn't support me at all. Extraordinary.
还有 安妮也不支持我了
And I'm not getting support from Annie.
真的? 定额的事?      提拔莎拉的事
Really? What, about this quota? Well, about promoting Sarah.
还以为她绝对支持呢      就是
You'd think she'd be 100% behind it. Indeed.
我一说她态度完全反了
She goes sort of distant when I mention it.
打死也不愿意      更怪了
Dead against it now. Even more extraordinary.
反正就这一件事了
Oh, well, seems the only thing left.
我力所能及的      对 没错
Something I can achieve. Yes, indeed.
请哈里森女士进来好吗? 伯纳 请去叫一下
Shall I ask Mrs Harrison to come in? Would you be kind enough?
至少是我值得一提的成就 汉弗莱
At least this is something I can say I have done.
没错 大臣      星星之火
Indeed. Lighting a spark.
可以燎原
Carrying a torch, even.
莎拉 请坐
Ah, Sarah, do sit down.
谢谢     汉弗莱     谢谢 大臣
Thank you. Humphrey.
莎拉 也许你听说了 副秘书有一个空缺
There is a vacancy for a Deputy Secretary in this department.
虽然你是资历最浅的秘书
In spite of you being the most junior Under-Secretary,
但因为你能力出众
but because you are the outstanding person,
汉弗莱爵士和我推荐你晋升为副秘书
Sir Humphrey and I have recommend you to Deputy Secretary.
我...我不知说什么好
I... I don't know what to say.
什么都不用说      一个谢谢就够了
No need to say anything. A single thank you should suffice.
不...嗯...我是说...
No... Well... I mean...
太难启齿了 我是说
Oh, gosh. Look, this is awfully embarrassing. I mean...
本来想这周告诉你们的 我要辞职了
I was going to tell you. I'm resigning from the Civil Service.
什么?      辞职?
What? Resigning?
对 所以...谢谢好意 我心领了
Yes, so... thank you, but no, thank you.
要照顾孩子?      腮腺炎?
Some problem at home with your children? Mumps?
不 我要进一家商业银行 做主管
No, I'm joining a merchant bank... as a director.
莎拉...我明说了吧 这里面另有文章
Sarah... I won't conceal from you the fact that this is a blow.
我和汉弗莱之所以举荐你
The reason Humphrey and I decided to recommend you
是因为增加女性定额的努力快失败了
I've been fighting a losing battle to improve promotion for women.
可以说是借用你来...当跳板
You were to be my, so to speak, Trojan horse.
老实说 大臣 我想干的工作不是没完没了
Quite honestly, I want a job where I don't spend endless hours
给无关人等就无关事项传递无关信息
Information about subjects don't matter to people aren't interested.
我想有所成就 不想整天忙那些文山会海
I want a job where there's achievement rather than merely activity.
我想指着什么东西自豪的说 "我做的"
I want to point to something and say "I did that."
我不明白
I don't understand.
我知道 所以我才要走
I know. That's why I'm leaving.
你觉得治理国家不重要?
You're not saying the government is unimportant?
当然重要 不过我没看到谁在治理国家
It's just that I haven't met anyone who's doing it.
再说 这些花招我也厌烦了
Also I've had enough of the pointless intrigue.
花招?      您明白的
Intrigue? You know the sort of thing.
比如女权这件事 您得靠我当跳板
Like this women's rights. Your using me as a Trojan horse.
他们大概跟您说工会反对提拔我
They probably said the unions wouldn't wear it if you promoted me.
你怎么知道的?      我不知道 这是惯用伎俩
How did you know that? I didn't. I just know how things are done.
你不知道我为你付出了多大努力
You don't realise I've fought quite a battle for you.
是吗? 我没要求您为我争取什么
Oh, have you? I didn't ask you to fight a battle for me.
我不想被当成25%定额
I'm not pleased at being part of a 25% quota.
女人不是低等人 我也不喜欢被施舍
Women are not inferior beings and I don't enjoy being patronised.
恐怕您和他们一样家长式 沙文主义
You're just as paternalist and chauvinist as the rest of them.
我要去一个平等的 把我当人看的地方
I'm going somewhere to be accepted an equal, as a person.
没出路的 是吗?
You can't win, can you?
我可以走了吗?      嗯? 当然
May I go now? Hm? Yes, of course.
很抱歉伤害了你的感情 虽然我没明白怎么回事
I'm sorry I offended you, though I can't remember how I did.
是没有
No.
谢谢 我知道你们出于好意
And thank you. I know you both mean well.
女人啊
Women!
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.